Guide to the School of Architecture, Yale University, Records of the Dean
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
School of Architecture, Yale University, records of the dean
1931-2016
RU 843
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
122.42
(134 boxes)
The records consist of printed material, reports, subject and committee files, correspondence, newspaper clippings, student publication, two DVDs "Student Resumes and Work Samples", one DVD "Kent and Nona Bloomer In-Coming Student Picnic", and course evaluations of the dean of the Yale School of Architecture. Topics include the renovation of the Art and Architecture building, re-accreditation of the school, and visiting critics.
Yale University. School of Architecture
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 19-A (YRG 19-A), Central records and records of the dean of the School of Architecture.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is partially restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of printed material, reports, subject and committee files, correspondence, newspaper clippings, student publication, two DVDs "Student Resumes and Work Samples", one DVD "Kent and Nona Bloomer In-Coming Student Picnic", and course evaluations of the dean of the Yale School of Architecture. Topics include the renovation of the Art and Architecture building, re-accreditation of the school, and visiting critics.
Architecture -- Study and teaching; College buildings -- Design and construction; Schools of architecture; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Curricula; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Buildings; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University. School of Architecture
- Program for the symposium titled "People of Color in Architecture", 1991; Accession 2002-A-083
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  - Program for the symposium titled "People of Color in Architecture", 1991 (Box 1)
- Records concerning visiting critics, circa 1947-1980; Accession 2006-A-039
  - Visiting Critics
    - 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Recommendations, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Robert A.M. Stern, dean of the School of Architecture, records, 1978, 2009-2012; Accession 2013-A-065
  Restricted until January 1, 2047
  - Correspondence
    - 2010 April-October (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - 2010 November-2011 February (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - 2011 January-December (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - 2011 March-May (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - Planning for First Year Studio, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Course Materials
    - General files
      - Course syllabi, readings and correspondence, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
      - Miscellaneous student papers for Dean Stern, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Undergraduate course evaluations, 2012 Fall (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Arch 3223a Parallels of the Modern
      - Fall 2009
        - Applications, 2009 Fall (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Dean Stern's course files, 2009 Fall (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - Evaluations and letter from Andrea Cocojaru, 2009 Fall (Box 1, Folder 17)
        - Student papers, 2009 Fall (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
      - Fall 2010
        - Class list and readings, 2010 Fall (Box 1, Folder 20)
        - Class readings, 2010 Fall (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
        - Student papers, 2010 Fall (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
        - Syllabi and non-ranked evaluations, 2010 Fall (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Fall 2011
        - Class lists and evaluations, 2011 Fall (Box 2, Folder 27)
        - Class lists, correspondence and student papers, 2011 Fall (Box 2, Folder 28)
        - Student papers, 2011 Fall (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Fall 2012
        - Student papers, 2012 Fall (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - Photographs
    - Paul Rudolph, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Ibaraki Prefecture Health Care Center-photograph and building construction statistics. Designed by Kazuhiro Ishii, Yale School of Architecture Class of 1975. (Box 3, Folder 33)
      General
      Oversize
- Robert A.M. Stern, dean of the School of Architecture, records, 1990-2014; Accession 2015-A-002
  Restricted until January 1, 2049
  - Architecture-work studio brochure, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Beyond Architecture: Bass Fellowship lecture by Isaac Kalisvaart, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Charles W. Moore memorial invitation, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - City Making at the Edge of Everywhere: Yale School of Architecture booklet, 2014 Spring (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1990-2013 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Final reviews schedule, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lecture series schedule of events, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Open house ephemera, 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Symposia ephemera, 1993-2014 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Navy Yard, Yale and Oosterdok: New Perspectives catalog, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - To Draw is to See: exhibit catalog, 2010-2013 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Yale Conference on Housing event program, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Yale School of Architecture news clippings, 2013-2014 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Year-end exhibition of student work ephemera, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Event poster: Sign/Symbol, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Event poster: Work in Process, 1996 Fall (Box 3)
  - test
- 1998 NAAB re-accreditation records, 1995-1998; Accession 2015-A-003
  Restricted until January 1, 2033
  - General
    - NAAB exhibit memoranda and notes, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Architectural Program Report
    - Final report, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Appendices, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Draft materials, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Evaluation summary, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Layouts, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Course description reports
    - Advanced Studio
      - 511a-Volker Gienke, House of the Tango Dancer, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 512b-Samuel Mockbee, Alabama, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 513b-Jose Antonio Acebillo, Completing the Sea Front of Barcelona, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - 514b-Daniel Hoffman, Manufactured Housing, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - 515a-Jeffrey King, Expansion of the Boston Athenaeum, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 517a-Peggy Deamer, Supermarket on the West Side Highway, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - 517a-George Ranalli, House/Art Studio, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - 518b-Judith Di Maio, Equestrian Center, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 519a-Thomas Hanrahan, Cinema, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - 519a-David Turnbull, HUB:/Ijub.slov, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - 520b-Deborah Berke, Speculative House, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - 521a-Fred Koetter, University of Puerto Rico, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - 522b-Steven Harris, Harvey Milk High School, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Core Studio
      - Core Studios-report drafts, correspondence and memoranda, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Core Studio I
        - 501a-Alec Purves, Steven Harris, Felecia Davis, Laura Kurgan, Architectural Design, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        - 501a-Alec Purves, Peggy Deamer, Steven Harris, Laura Kurgan, Architectural Design, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Core Studio II
        - 502b-Jeffrey King, Louise Harpman, Turner Brooks, David Turnbull, Architectural Design, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        - 502b-Paul Brouard, Building Project, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Core Studio III
        - 503a-Barbara Littenberg, Victor Body-Lawson, Michael Haverland, Alan Plattus, Architectural Design, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        - 503a-Barbara Littenberg, Michael Haverland, Fred Koetter, Alan Plattus, Housing and Urban Form, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Core Studio IV
        - 504a-George Ranalli, Swimming Pool, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        - 504b-M.J. Long, Boat Museum, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - 504b-Peter de Bretteville, Foote School, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 30)
        - 504b-Patrick Pinnell, Science Museum, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Elective courses
      - 614b-James Axley, Structures and Architecture: Polemics and Practice, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - 636b-Donald Watson, Design Technology Workshop, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - 637a-King-Lui Wu, Daylight in Architecture, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - 668b-Donald Baerman, Critical Architectural Systems, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
      - 676b-Peter Millard, Transportation of Information in Architectural Design, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - 680b-Thomas Beeby, Architecture as Building, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - 681a-Peter de Bretteville, Furniture Design and Fabrication, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - 682b-Kent Bloomer, Furniture Design and Fabrication, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - 685a-Philip G. Bernstein, Architectural Project Management with Computers, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - 686b-Philip G. Bernstein, Advanced Topics in Project Management, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - 703a-Peggy Deamer, Contemporary Architectural Theory, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - 751a-Kent Bloomer, Ornament Theory and Design, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - 756b-Eva-Liisa Pelkonen, Architecture and Politics: Strategies of the 20th Century Avant-Gardes, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - 758b-Eva-Liisa Pelkonen, Rethinking Modern Tradition: Contempotary Debates, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - 762b-Jeffrey Klug, Assembly as a Vehicle for Speculation, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - 764b-Peter de Bretteville, Studies in Architectural Analysis: Industrial Buildings in Connecticut, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - 766b-Peter de Bretteville, Studies in Architectural Analysis: Campus Planning, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - 776b-Esther de Costa Meyer, Cinema and Architecture, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - 772b-Sylvia Kolbowski, Architecture and Art: A Parallactic View, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 51)
      - 791a-Jeffrey Klug, The Art of the City: Summer Seminar in Rome, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      - 805a-Stephen Hicks, Drawing from the Architectural Landscape, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      - 806b-Turner Brooks, Drawing, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      - 807b-Philip Grausman, Advanced Drawing, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      - 813a-Robert Espejo, Photography for Architects, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      - 851a-Robert Frew, Introduction to 3-D Modeling and Visualization, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 57)
      - 853a/854b-David Chen and Roberta Weinberg, Drawing Using AutoCAD, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      - 855a Carol Scully, Digital Video Synthesis, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 59)
        See also: box 4.
      - 871a-Joon Lee, Advanced Modeling and Animation, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 60)
      - 881a Laura Kurgan, Multimedia Architecture: Drawing, Computing, Building, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      - 882b-Robert Frew and Joon Lee, Topics in Computer-Aided Design, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      - 906b-Alexander Garvin, Intermediate Planning and Development, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 63)
      - 911a-Alan Plattus, The Public Realm: A Critical History of Urban Space, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      - 912b-Dolores Hayden, Introduction to the History of the Urban Landscape in the United States, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      - 914b-Dolores Hayden, Seminar in Cultural Landscape History, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 66)
      - 916b-Michael Haverland, Architecture and the Urban Community, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 67)
      - 917a-Michael Haverland and Alan Plattus, Joint Community Development Clinic, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 68)
      - 918b-Michael Haverland, Neighborhood Clinic: Dwight Elementary School Addition Design Seminar, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 924b-Alan Plattus, Paris: Architecture and Urban Culture from St. Louis to Mitterand, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 925a-Dolores Hayden, The American Suburb, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous courses [electives], 1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Independent Studio
      - Jennifer Smith and Greg Lewis-Greenport Harbor competition, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Carl Bergamini and Marjorie Dickstein-Trumbull Shopping Mall, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Required courses
      - Report drafts and memoranda, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - 508b-James Axley and Everett Barber, Systems Integration and Development in Design, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 603a-James Axley, Structural Engineering, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 666b-Harold Roth, Architectural Practice, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 702b-Joeb Moore, Architectural Theory, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 801a-Laura Kurgan, Visual Studies I (Drawing), 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - 802A-Philip Grausman, Freehand Drawing, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - 804b-George Ranalli and Anthony Markese, Descriptive Geometry, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - 810b-Kent Bloomer, Actual 3-D, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - 904b-Alexander Garvin, Introduction to Planning and Development, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Digital Video Student Work, 1995-1997; 1 (Box 4)
    See box 1 folder 59
- Dean of the School of Architecture records concerning former faculty, 1965-2013; Accession 2015-A-006
  Restricted until January 1, 2088